<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-kitterman-dmarc-tld-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     updates="7489">

 <front>
   <title abbrev="TLD DMARC">DMARC (Domain-based Message Authentication, 
       Reporting, and Conformance) Extension For TLDs (Top Level Domains)
   </title>

   <author initials="S." surname="Kitterman"
	   fullname="Scott Kitterman">
      <organization>Kitterman Technical Services</organization>

      <address>
	 <postal>
	    <street>3611 Scheel Dr</street>
	    <city>Ellicott City</city>
	    <region>MD</region>
	    <code>21042</code>
	    <country>United States of America</country>
	 </postal>
	    
	 <phone>+1 301 325-5475</phone>
	 <email>scott@kitterman.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>

   <date month="August" year="2018" />

   <keyword>DMARC</keyword>
   <keyword>email authentication</keyword>
   <keyword>TLD</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>DMARC (Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and Conformance) 
         is a scalable mechanism by which a mail-originating organization can
         express domain-level policies and preferences for message validation,
         disposition, and reporting, that a mail-receiving organization can use
         to improve mail handling.  DMARC itself does not apply to TLDs (Top
         Level Domains).  For the subset of TLDs that require DMARC usage, it is
         appropriate to provide TLD level DMARC capability.  This memo describes
         an extension to DMARC to enable a subset of DMARC functionality for
         such TLDs.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
     <t><xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> provides email sending
         organizational policy information to email receivers.  Due to the
         design of <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> and the nature of the
         Internet <xref target="RFC5598">email architecture</xref>, there are
         interoperability issues associated with <xref target="RFC7489">
         DMARC</xref> deployment.  These are discused in <xref target="RFC7960">
         Interoperability Issues between DMARC and Indirect Email Flows</xref>.
         These issues are not applicable to TLDs, since they do not send mail.
     </t>

     <t><xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>, by design, does not support
         requirements of TLD operators.  For TLDs that require use of
         <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>, a subset of DMARC reporting and
         enforcement capability is needed for TLD operators to effectively
         manage and monitor implementation of TLD requirements.
     </t>
     
     <t>Additionally, the ability to extend <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>
         policy to operate against non-existent domains would enhance its
         utility for TLD Operators as well as Domain Owners.  Originally,
         <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> included this functionality, but it
         was removed after significant operational issues were discovered.  This
         memo adds a new <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> record tag to
         provide this capability on an optional, opt-in basis.
     </t>

   </section>
   
   <section title="Terminology and Definitions">
       <t>This section defines terms used in the rest of the document.
       </t>
       <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
           <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
               NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
               "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
               described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
               <xref target="RFC8174"/>  when, and only when, they appear in all
               capitals, as shown here.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="Top Level Domain (TLD)">
           <t>The global Internet Domain Name System (DNS) is documented in
               numerous Requests for Comment (RFC).  It defines a tree of names
               starting with root, ".", immediately below which are Top Level
               Domain names such as ".com" and ".us".
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="TLD Operator (TLDO)">
           <t>A TLD Operator manages operations within their TLD based on
               guidance and rules from ICANN (Internet Corporation for Assigned
               Names and Numbers).
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="TLDO Controlled Domain Names">
           <t>TLDO Controlled Domain Names are names in the DNS that are
               managed by TLDOs and not available for use as organizational
               domains (the term organizational domains is defined in <xref
               target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>).  Depending on TLD policy, these
               will have one (e.g. ".com") or more (e.g. ".co.uk") or more name
               components.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="Non-existent Domains">
           <t>For <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> purposes, a non-existent
               domain is a domain name that publishes none of A, AAAA, or MX
               records.  This is a broader definition than that in <xref
               target="RFC8020">NXDOMAIN</xref>.
           </t>
       </section>
   </section>

   <section title="TLD DMARC Updates to DMARC Requirements">

     <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> as follows:</t>

     <section title="General Updates">
         <t>References to "Domain Owners" also apply to TLDOs.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.1 DMARC Policy Record">
         <t>TLD DMARC records are published as a subdomain of the TLD.  For the
             TLD ".example", the TLDO would post DMARC preferences in a TXT
             record at "_dmarc.example".
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.3.  General Record Format">
         <t>The rf and ruf tags are not applicable to TLD DMARC and MUST be
             ignored for TLD records.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.5.  Domain Owner Actions">
         <t>In addition to the <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> domain owner
             actions, TLDOs will need to update the "DMARC TLD Registry".  See
             IANA Considerations below.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.6.3.  Policy Discovery">
         <t>A new step between step 3 and 4 is added:</t>
         <t><list style="hanging">
               <t hangText="3A.">If the set is now empty and the TLD of the
                   Organizational Domain is listed in the DMARC TLD Registry,
                   the Mail Receiver MUST query the DNS for a DMARC TXT record
                   at the DNS domain matching the TLD in place of the
                   RFC5322.From domain in the message (if different).  This
                   record can contain policy to be asserted for subdomains of
                   the TLD.  A possibly empty set of records is returned.
               </t>
         </list> </t>
     </section>
     <section title="7.2.  Aggregate Reports">
         <t>NOTE: We would like to modify this section to allow multiple
             nxdomain subdomain reports to be reported in a single report.  This
             would also require changes in the Appendix C XML schema.  Recommend
             defering this to discussion in the IETF DMARC working group where
             the authors of the original design that disallows this can weigh
             in.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="7.3.  Failure Reports">
         <t>This section is not applicable to records identified via policy
             discovery step 3A.
         </t>
     </section>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Non-existent Domain Requirements">
       <section title="Section 6.3.  General Record Format">
           <t>A new "np" tag is added:</t>
           <t><list style="hanging">
               <t hangText="np:">Requested Mail Receiver policy for all
                   non-existent domains (plain-text; OPTIONAL).  Indicates the
                   policy to be enacted by the Receiver at
      the request of the Domain Owner.  It applies only to subdomains of the
      domain queried and not to the domain itself.  Its syntax is identical to
      that of the "p" tag defined above.  If absent, DMARC policy MUST NOT be
      applied for non-existent domains.</t>
           </list> </t>
       </section>
   </section>

   <section title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t> This document does not change significantly change the Privacy
          Considerations of <xref target="RFC7489"/>.  Privacy considerations
          related to Failure Reports do not apply to TLD DMARC.
      </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This document does not change the Security Considerations of
      <xref target="RFC7489"/>.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="IANA Considerations">
       <t>This section describes actions requested to be completed by IANA.</t>

       <section title="DMARC Tag Registry Update">
           <t>IANA is requested to add the following item to the registry:</t>
            <texttable>
                <ttcol align="center">Tag Name</ttcol>
                <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
                <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
                <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
                <c>np</c>
                <c>this document</c>
                <c>current</c>
                <c>Requested handling policy for non-existent domains</c>
            </texttable>
       </section>
       <section title="DMARC Top Level Domain (TLD) Registry">
           <t>IANA is requested to create a new DMARC Top Level Domain (TLD)
               Registry within the Domain-based Message Authentication,
               Reporting, and Conformance (DMARC) Parameters Registry.
           </t>
           <t>Names of TLDs participating in TLD DMARC must be registered with
               IANA in this new sub-registry.  New entries are assigned only for
               TLDs that require use of DMARC.  The requirement has to be
               documented in a manner that satisfies the terms of Expert Review,
               per <xref target="RFC5226"/>.  The Designated Expert needs to
               confirm that provided documentation adequately describes TLD
               policy to require domain owners to use DMARC.
           </t>
           <t>The initial set of entries in this registry is as follows:
            <figure><artwork>
+-------------+----------------+---------------+
|    TLD      | Reference      | Status        |
+-------------+----------------+---------------+
| .bank       | this document  | current       |
+-------------+----------------+---------------+
| .insurance  | this document  | current       |
+-------------+----------------+---------------+
                                </artwork> </figure>
           </t>
       </section>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7489" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174" ?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5598" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7960" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8020" ?>

   </references>
   <section anchor="thanks" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t> TBS </t>
    </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
