<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="exp"
     docName="draft-ietf-dmarc-psd-07"
     ipr="trust200902">

 <front>
   <title abbrev="PSD DMARC">DMARC (Domain-based Message Authentication, 
       Reporting, and Conformance) Extension For PSDs (Public Suffix Domains)
   </title>

   <author initials="S." surname="Kitterman"
	   fullname="Scott Kitterman">
      <organization>fTLD Registry Services</organization>

      <address>
	 <postal>
	    <street>600 13th Street, NW, Suite 400</street>
	    <city>Washington</city>
	    <region>DC</region>
	    <code>20005</code>
	    <country>United States of America</country>
	 </postal>
	    
	 <phone>+1 301 325-5475</phone>
	 <email>scott@kitterman.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>

   <date month="September" year="2019" />

   <keyword>DMARC</keyword>
   <keyword>email authentication</keyword>
   <keyword>TLD</keyword>

   <abstract>
      <t>DMARC (Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and
         Conformance) is a scalable mechanism by which a mail-originating
         organization can express domain-level policies and preferences for
         message validation, disposition, and reporting, that a mail-receiving
         organization can use to improve mail handling.  The design of DMARC
         presumes that domain names represent either nodes in the tree below
         which registrations occur, or nodes where registrations have occurred;
         it does not permit a domain name to have both of these properties
         simultaneously.  Since its deployment in 2015, use of DMARC has shown
         a clear need for the ability to express policy for these domains as
         well.</t>
      <t>Domains at which registrations can occur are referred to as Public
         Suffix Domains (PSDs).  This document describes an extension to DMARC
         to enable DMARC functionality for PSDs.</t>
      <t>This document also seeks to address implementations that consider a
         domain on a public Suffix list to be ineligible for DMARC
         enforcement.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
     <t><xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> provides a mechanism for
         publishing organizational policy information to email receivers.
         DMARC allows policy to be specified for both individual domains and
         for organizational domains and their sub-domains within a single
         organization.  DMARC leverages public suffix lists to determine which
         domains are organizational domains.  It presumes that public suffix
         list listed domains are not organizational domains and not subject to
         DMARC processing; domains are either organizational domains,
         sub-domains of organizational domains, or listed on a public suffix
         list.  For domains listed in a public suffix list, i.e. TLDs and
         domains that exist between TLDs and organization level domains,
         policy can only be published for the exact domain.  No method is
         available for these domains to express policy or receive feedback
         reporting for sub-domains.  This missing method allows for the abuse
         of non-existent organizational-level domains and prevents
         identification of domain abuse in email.
     </t>
     <t> As an example, imagine a country code TLD (ccTLD) which has public
         subdomains for government and commercial use (.gov.example and
         .com.example).  Suppose there exists a registered domain
         "tax.gov.example" that is responsible for taxation in this imagined
         country.  However, by exploiting the typically unauthenticated nature of
         email, there are regular malicious campaigns to impersonate this
         organization that use similar-looking ("cousin") domains such as
         "t4x.gov.example".  These domains are not registered.  Within the
         ".gov.example" public suffix, use of DMARC has been mandated, so
         "gov.example" publishes the following DMARC record:
         <figure><artwork>
"v=DMARC1; p=reject; rua=mailto:dmarc@dmarc.service.gov.example"
        </artwork></figure>
         at
         <figure><artwork>
_dmarc.gov.example.
         </artwork></figure>
         This DMARC record provides policy and a reporting destination for
         mail sent from @gov.example. However, due to DMARC's current method
         of discovering and applying policy at the organizational domain
         level, the non-existent organizational domain of @tax.gov.example
         does not and cannot fall under a DMARC policy.
     </t>
     <t> Defensively registering all variants of "tax" is obviously not a scalable
         strategy.  The intent of this specification, therefore, is to enhance the
         DMARC algorithm by enabling an agent receiving such a message to be able to
         determine that a relevant policy is present at "gov.example", which is
         precluded by the current DMARC algorithm.
     </t>
     <t> This document provides a simple extension to <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC
         </xref> to allow operators of Public Suffix Domains (PSDs) to express
	 policy at the level of the PSD that covers all organizational domains
	 that do not explicitly publish DMARC records, extends the DMARC
     policy query functionality to detect
	 and process such a policy, describes receiver feedback for such
	 policies, and provides controls to mitigate potential privacy
	 considerations associated with this extension.
     </t>
     <t>This document also provides a new <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> tag
	to indicate requested handling policy for non-existent subdommains.
	This is provided specifically to support phased deployment of PSD
	DMARC, but is expected to be useful more generally.  Undesired
	rejection risks for mail purporting to be from domains that do not
	exist are substantially lower than for those that do, so the
	operational risk of requesting harsh policy treatment (e.g. reject) is
	lower.
     </t>
     <t>As an additional benefit, the PSD DMARC extension clarifies
	existing requirements.  Based on the requirements of <xref
        target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>, DMARC should function above the
        organizational level for exact domain matches (i.e. if a DMARC record
        were published for 'example', then mail from example@example should be
        subject to DMARC processing).  Testing had revealed that this is not
        consistently applied in different implementations.
     </t>
     <t>There are two types of Public Suffix Operators (PSOs) for which this
         extension would be useful and appropriate:
     </t>
         <t><list style="symbols">
                  <t>Branded PSDs (e.g., ".google"): These domains are
                      effectively Organizational Domains as discussed in <xref
                      target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>.  They control all
                      subdomains of the tree.  These are effectively private
                      domains, but listed in the Public Suffix List.  They are
                      treated as Public for DMARC
                      purposes.  They require the same protections as DMARC
                      Organizational Domains, but are currently unable to
                      benefit from DMARC.
                  </t>
                  <t>Multi-organization PSDs that require DMARC usage (e.g.,
                      ".bank"):  Because existing Organizational Domains using
                      this PSD have their own DMARC policy, the applicability of
                      this extension is for non-existent domains.  The extension
                      allows the brand protection benefits of DMARC to extend to
                      the entire PSD,
                      including cousin domains of registered organizations.
                  </t>
          </list></t>
     <t>Due to the design of <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> and the nature
         of the Internet <xref target="RFC5598">email architecture</xref>, there
         are interoperability issues associated with <xref target="RFC7489">
         DMARC</xref> deployment.  These are discussed in <xref target="RFC7960">
         Interoperability Issues between DMARC and Indirect Email Flows</xref>.
         These issues are not typically applicable to PSDs, since they (e.g., the
         ".gov.example" used above) do not typically send mail.
     </t>

   </section>

   <section title="Terminology and Definitions">
       <t>This section defines terms used in the rest of the document.
       </t>
       <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
           <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
               NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
               "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
               described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
               <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
               capitals, as shown here.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="Public Suffix Domain (PSD)">
           <t> The global Internet Domain Name System (DNS) is documented in
               numerous Requests for Comment (RFC).  It defines a tree of names
               starting with root, ".", immediately below which are Top Level
               Domain names such as ".com" and ".us".  They are not available
               for private registration.  In many cases the public portion of
               the DNS tree is more than one level deep.
               
               The domain name structure consists of a tree of names, each of
               which is made of a sequence of words ("labels") separated by
               period characters.  The root of the tree is simply called ".".
               The Internet community at large, through processes and policies
               external to this work, selects points in this tree at which to
               register domain names "owned" by independent organizations.
               Real-world examples are ".com", ".org", ".us", and ".gov.uk".
               Names at which such registrations occur are called Public
               Suffix Domains (PSDs), and a registration consists of a label
               selected by the registrant to which a desirable PSD is
               appended.  For example, "ietf.org" is a registered domain name,
               and ".org" is its PSD.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section anchor="lpsd" title="Longest PSD">
           <t> The longest PSD is the Organizational Domain with one label
               removed.</t>
       </section>
       <section title="Public Suffix Operator (PSO)">
           <t>A Public Suffix Operator manages operations within its PSD.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="PSO Controlled Domain Names">
           <t>PSO Controlled Domain Names are names in the DNS that are
               managed by a PSO and are not available for use as Organizational
               Domains (the term Organizational Domains is defined in <xref
               target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> Section 3.2).  Depending on PSD policy, these
               will have one (e.g., ".com") or more (e.g., ".co.uk") name
               components.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section title="Non-existent Domains">
           <t>For DMARC purposes, a non-existent
	      domain is a domain for which there is an NXDOMAIN or NODATA
	      response for A, AAAA, and MX records.  This is a broader definition
	      than that in <xref target="RFC8020">NXDOMAIN</xref>.
           </t>
       </section>
   </section>

   <section title="PSD DMARC Updates to DMARC Requirements">

     <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> as follows:</t>

     <section title="General Updates">
         <t>References to "Domain Owners" also apply to PSOs.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.3 General Record Format">
	 <t>A new tag is added after "fo":</t>
	 <t><list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="np:"> Requested Mail Receiver policy for non-existent
	     subdomains (plain-text; OPTIONAL).  Indicates the policy to be
	     enacted by the Receiver at the request of the Domain Owner.  It
	     applies only to non-existent subdomains of the domain queried and
	     not to either existing subdomains or the domain itself.  Its
	     syntax is identical to that of the "p" tag defined below.  If
	     the 'np' tag is absent, the policy specified by the "sp" tag (if
	     the 'sp' tag is present) or the policy specified by the "p" tag,
	     if the 'sp' tag is not present, MUST be applied for non-existent
	     subdomains.  Note that "np" will be ignored for DMARC records
	     published on subdomains of Organizational Domains and PSDs due to
	     the effect of the DMARC policy discovery mechanism described in
	     <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref> Section 6.6.3.
	    </t>
         </list></t>
	 <t>The following tag definitions from <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>
	    are updated:
	 </t>
	 <t><list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="p:">The sentence 'Policy applies to the domain queried
	      and to subdomains, unless subdomain policy is explicitly described
	      using the "sp" tag' is updated to read 'Policy applies to the domain
              queried and to subdomains, unless subdomain policy is explicitly
              described using the "sp" or "np" tags.'
	    </t>
	    <t hangText="sp:">The sentence 'If absent, the policy specified by
	      the "p" tag MUST be applied for subdomains' is updated to read
	      'If both the 'sp' tag is absent and the 'np' tag is either absent
	      or not applicable, the policy specified by the "p" tag MUST be
	      applied for subdomains.
	    </t>
         </list></t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.5.  Domain Owner Actions">
         <t>In addition to the DMARC domain owner actions, PSOs that require
             use of DMARC and participate in PSD DMARC ought to make that
	         information available to receivers.  The mechanism for doing so is
             one of the experimental elements of this document.  See the <xref
             target="experiment">experiment description</xref>.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.6.1.  Extract Author Domain">
         <t> Experience with DMARC has shown that some implementations
             short-circuit messages, bypassing DMARC policy application, when
             the domain name extracted by the receiver (from the RFC5322.From)
             is on the public suffix list used by the receiver.  This
             negates the capability being created by this specification.
             Therefore, the following paragraph is appended to Section 6.6.1
             of <xref target="RFC7489">DMARC</xref>:
         </t>
         <t> Note that domain names that appear on a public suffix list are
             not exempt from DMARC policy application and reporting.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 6.6.3.  Policy Discovery">
         <t>A new step between step 3 and 4 is added:</t>
         <t><list style="hanging">
               <t hangText="3A.">If the set is now empty and the <xref
                   target="lpsd">longest PSD</xref> of the  Organizational
                   Domain is one that the receiver has determined is acceptable
		           for PSD DMARC (discussed in the <xref
                   target="experiment">experiment description</xref>), the Mail
                   Receiver MUST query the DNS for a DMARC TXT record at the DNS
                   domain matching the <xref target="lpsd">longest PSD</xref> in
                   place of the RFC5322.From domain in the message (if
                   different).  A possibly empty set of records is returned.
               </t>
         </list> </t>
         <t>As an example, for a message with the Organizational Domain of
             "example.compute.cloudcompany.com.example", the query for PSD DMARC
             would use "compute.cloudcompany.com.example" as the <xref
             target="lpsd">longest PSD</xref>.  The receiver would check to see
             if that PSD is listed in the DMARC PSD Registry, and if so, perform
             the policy lookup at "_dmarc.compute.cloudcompany.com.example".
         </t>
         <t>Note: Because the PSD policy query comes after the Organizational
             Domain policy query, PSD policy is not used for Organizational
             domains that have published a DMARC policy.  Specifically, this
             is not a mechanism to provide feedback addresses (RUA/RUF) when
             an Organizational Domain has declined to do so.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Section 7.  DMARC Feedback">
         <t> Operational note for PSD DMARC: For PSOs, feedback for non-existent
	     domains is desirable and useful, just as it is for org-level
	     DMARC operators.  See <xref target="privacy"/> of this document for
         discussion of Privacy Considerations.
         </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>These privacy considerations are developed based on the requirements of
          <xref target="RFC6973"/>.  The Privacy Considerations of <xref
          target="RFC7489"/> apply to this document.
      </t>
      <section anchor="leakage" title="Feedback leakage">
          <t>Providing feedback reporting to PSOs can, in some cases, create
              leakage of information outside of an organization to the PSO.
	      This leakage could potentially be utilized as part of a program
	      of pervasive surveillance (See <xref target="RFC7624"/>).  There
	      are roughly three cases to consider:
          </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
                  <t>Single Organization PSDs (e.g., ".google"), RUA and RUF
		      reports based on PSD DMARC have the potential to contain
		      information about emails related to entities managed by
		      the organization.  Since both the PSO and the
                      Organizational Domain owners are common, there is no
                      additional privacy risk for either normal or non-existent
		      Domain reporting due to PSD DMARC.
                  </t>
                  <t>Multi-organization PSDs that require DMARC usage (e.g.,
                      ".bank"):  PSD DMARC based reports will only be generated
                      for domains that do not publish a DMARC policy at the
                      organizational or host level.  For domains that do publish
                      the required DMARC policy records, the feedback reporting
                      addresses (RUA and RUF) of the organization (or hosts)
                      will be used.  The only direct feedback leakage risk for
		      these PSDs are for Organizational Domains that are out of
		      compliance with PSD policy.  Data on non-existent cousin
		      domains would be sent to the PSO.
                  </t>
                  <t>Multi-organization PSDs (e.g., ".com") that do not mandate
                      DMARC usage:  Privacy risks for Organizational Domains
                      that have not deployed DMARC within such PSDs are
		      significant.  For non-DMARC Organizational Domains, all
		      DMARC feedback will be directed to the PSO.  PSD DMARC is
		      opt-out (by publishing a DMARC record at the
		      Organizational Domain level) vice opt-in, which would be
		      the more desirable characteristic.  This means that any
		      non-DMARC organizational domain would have its feedback
		      reports redirected to the PSO.  The content of such
		      reports, particularly for existing domains, is privacy
		      sensitive.
                  </t>
          </list></t>
          <t>PSOs will receive feedback on non-existent domains, which may be
              similar to existing Organizational Domains.  Feedback related to
              such cousin domains have a small risk of carrying information
              related to an actual Organizational Domain.  To minimize this
              potential concern, PSD DMARC feedback is best limited to
              Aggregate Reports.  Feedback Reports carry more detailed
              information and present a greater risk.
          </t>
	  <t>Due to the inherent Privacy and Security risks associated with
	      PSD DMARC for Organizational Domains in multi-organization PSDs
	      that do not particpate in DMARC, any Feedback Reporting related to
	      multi-organizational PSDs ought to be limited to non-existent
	      domains except in cases where the reporter knows that PSO
	      requires use of DMARC.
	  </t>
       </section>
   </section>

   <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This document does not change the Security Considerations of
          <xref target="RFC7489"/> and <xref target="RFC7960"/>.
      </t>
      <t> The risks of the issues identified in <xref target="RFC7489"/>,
	  Section 12.3, DNS Security, are amplified by PSD DMARC.  In
	  particular, DNS cache poisoning (or Name Chaining), see <xref
	  target="RFC3833"/> for details, consequences are increased because a
	  sucessful attack would potentially have a much wider scope.
      </t>
      <t> The risks of the issues identified in <xref target="RFC7489"/>,
	  Section 12.5, External Reporting Addresses, are amplified by PSD
	  DMARC.  By design, PSD DMARC causes unrequested reporting of feedback
	  to entities external to the Organizational Domain.  This is discussed
	  in more detail in <xref target="privacy"/>.
      </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
       <t>This section describes actions requested to be completed by IANA.</t>

       <section anchor="iana1" title="Subdomain Policy Tag">
           <t>IANA is requested to add a new tag to DMARC Tag Registry in the Domain-based Message Authentication,
               Reporting, and Conformance (DMARC) Parameters Registry.
           </t>
           <t>The entry is as follows:
            <figure><artwork>
+----------+-----------+---------+-------------------------------+
| Tag Name | Reference | Status  | Description                   |
+----------+-----------+---------+-------------------------------+
| np       | this      | current | Requested handling policy for |
|          | document  |         | non-existent subdomains       |
+----------+-----------+---------+-------------------------------+
            </artwork> </figure>
           </t>
       </section>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7489" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174" ?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3833" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5598" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6973" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7624" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7960" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8020" ?>
      <reference anchor="PSL" target="https://publicsuffix.org/">
         <front>
            <title>Public Suffix List</title>
            <author>
               <organization>multiple</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2019" />
         </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="psddmarc.org" target="https://psddmarc.org/">
         <front>
            <title>PSD DMARC Web Site</title>
            <author>
               <organization>multiple</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2019" />
         </front>
      </reference>

   </references>

   <section anchor="experiment" title="The Experiment">
      <t> There are two experimental questions addressed in this document: one
	  regarding mitigation of PSD related privacy concerns and the other
	  on the utility of specifying separate DMARC policies for non-existent
	      sub-domains.</t>
      <t> Aditionally, as of the writing of this document operational and
          policy constraints prevent this experiment from being deployed
          globally. If the experiment shows that PSD DMARC solves a real
          problem and can be used at a large scale, the results could prove
          to be useful in removing constraints outside of the IETF that would
          permit broader deployment.
      </t>
      <section title="PSD DMARC Privacy Concern Mitigation">
      <t> To mitigate the privacy concerns associated with Multi-organization
	  PSDs that do not mandate DMARC usage, see <xref target="leakage"/>,
	  a mechanism to indicate which PSDs do not present this privacy risk is
	  appropriate.  There are multiple approaches that are possible.
      </t>
      <t> The experiment is to evaluate different possible approaches.  The
	  experiment will be complete when there is rough consensus on a
	  technical approach that is demonstrated to be operationally usable and
	  effective at mitigating the privacy concern.
      </t>
      <t> The mechanism needs the following attributes: </t>
	  <t><list style="symbols">
		  <t> Be reliably, publicly accessible</t>
		  <t> Be under configuration control based on a public set of
		      criteria
		  </t>
		  <t> List PSDs that either mandate DMARC for their registrants
		      or for which all lower level domains are controlled by the
		      PSO and that the relevant PSO has indicated a desire for
		      the PSD to participate in PSD DMARC
		  </t>
		  <t> Have a small operational footprint (e.g. provide a
		      documented, lightweight mechanism for developers and
		      operators to retrieve the list of PSD DMARC participants)
		  </t>
		  <t> Not allow PSO to add PSDs to the PSD DMARC participants
		      list without third party review
		  </t>
	  </list></t>
      <t> As of this writing, three approaches have been proposed.  None of them
	  are ideal:
      </t>
	  <t><list style="symbols">
		  <t> An extension to the Public Suffix List at <xref
		      target="PSL"/>
		  </t>
		  <t> A dedicated registry queried via DNS - an example of such
		      a service is described in <xref target="dnsregistry"/> below
		  </t>
		  <t> An IANA registry</t>
	  </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Non-Existent Subdomain Policy">
	<t> PSOs that plan to implement PSD DMARC have indicated that the
            ability to describe distinct policies for existing and non-
	    existing sub-domains would facilitate PSD DMARC deployment.  There
	    are also suggestions that it would be more generally useful for
	    DMARC.
	</t>
	<t> During the period of the experiment, uptake of the new 'np' tag
	    will be evaluated to support assessment of the utility of
	    including 'np' in a future, non-experimental update.
	</t>
      </section>
   </section>
   <section anchor="registry" title="DMARC PSD Registry Examples">
	   <t> To facilitate experimentation around data leakage mitigation, samples
	       of the DNS based and IANA like registries are available at
	       <xref target="psddmarc.org"/>.
           </t>
	<section anchor="dnsregistry" title="DMARC PSD DNS Query Service">
	   <t> A sample stand-alone DNS query service is available at <xref
	       target="psddmarc.org"/>.  It was developed based on the contents
	       suggested for an IANA registry in an earlier revision of this draft.
	       Usage of the service is described on the web site.
           </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana2" title="DMARC Public Suffix Domain (PSD) Registry">
	   <t> <xref target="psddmarc.org"/> provides an IANA like DMARC Public
	       Suffix Domain (PSD) Registry as a stand-alone DNS query service.  It
	       follows the contents and structure described below.  There is a Comma
	       Separated Value (CSV) version of the listed PSD domains which is
	       suitable for use in build updates for PSD DMARC capable software.
           </t>
           <t>Names of PSDs participating in PSD DMARC must be registered this
	       new registry.  New entries are assigned only for PSDs that
	       require use of DMARC.  The requirement has to be documented in a
	       manner that satisfies the terms of Expert Review,per <xref
	       target="RFC5226"/>.  The Designated Expert needs to confirm that
	       provided documentation adequately describes PSD policy to require
	       domain owners to use DMARC or that all domain owners are part of
	       a single organization with the PSO.
           </t>
           <t>The initial set of entries in this registry is as follows:
            <figure><artwork>
+-------------+---------------+
|    PSD      | Status        |
+-------------+---------------+
| .bank       | current       |
+-------------+---------------+
| .insurance  | current       |
+-------------+---------------+
| .gov.uk     | current       |
+-------------+---------------+
                                </artwork> </figure>
           </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="pslplus" title="DMARC PSD PSL Extension">
           <t> <xref target="psddmarc.org"/> provides a PSL like file to enable to
               facilitate identification of PSD DMARC participants.  Contents are
               functionally identical to the IANA like registry, but presented in
               a different format.
           </t>
	   <t> When using this approach, the input domain of the extension lookup
               is supposed to be the output domain of the regular PSL lookup, i.e.
               the organizational domain.  This alternative data approach is
               potentially useful since DMARC implementations already need to be
               able to parse the data format, so it should be easier to implement.
           </t>
        </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="implementation" title="Implementation">
      <t> There are two known implementations of PSD DMARC available for testing.
      </t>
      <section title="Authheaders Module">
	 <t>The authheaders Python module and command line tool is available
	    for download or installation from Pypi (Python Packaging Index).
         </t>
	 <t>It supports both use of the DNS based query service and download
	    of the CSV registry file from <xref target="psddmarc.org"/>.
         </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Zdkimfilter Module">
	 <t>The zdkimfilter module is a separately available add-on to
            Courier-MTA.
	 </t>
	 <t>Mostly used for DKIM signing, it can be configured to also verify,
            apply DMARC policies, and send aggregate reports.  For PSD DMARC
            it uses the PSL extension list approach, which is available from
            from <xref target="psddmarc.org"/>
         </t>
      </section>
   </section>
   <section anchor="thanks" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t> Thanks to the following individuals for their contributions (both
	  public and private) to improving this document.  Special shout out to
	  Dave Crocker for naming the beast.</t>
      <t> Kurt Andersen, Seth Blank, Dave Crocker, Heather Diaz, Tim Draegen,
	  Zeke Hendrickson, Andrew Kennedy, John Levine, Dr Ian Levy, Craig
	  Schwartz, Alessandro Vesely, and Tim Wicinski</t>
    </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
